<Chapter><Heading>Simplicial complexes &amp; CW complexes</Heading>
<Section><Heading>The Klein bottle as a simplicial complex</Heading>

<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="images/klein.jpg" align="center" width="250" alt="Klein bottle"/>
&lt;img src="images/kleingrid.jpg" align="center" width="250"/ alt="simplicial Klein bottle"></Alt>

<P/> The following example constructs the Klein bottle as a simplicial complex <M>K</M> on <M>9</M> vertices, and then constructs the cellular chain complex
<M>C_\ast=C_\ast(K)</M> from which the integral homology groups
 <M>H_1(K,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z_2\oplus \mathbb Z</M>, <M>H_2(K,\mathbb Z)=0</M> are computed. The  chain complex 
<M>D_\ast=C_\ast \otimes_{\mathbb Z} \mathbb Z_2</M> is also constructed and used to compute the mod-<M>2</M> homology vector spaces
<M>H_1(K,\mathbb Z_2)=\mathbb Z_2\oplus \mathbb Z_2</M>, <M>H_2(K,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z_2</M>.
Finally, a presentation  <M>\pi_1(K) = \langle
x,y : yxy^{-1}x\rangle</M> is computed for the fundamental group of <M>K</M>. 

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.1.txt">
</Example>

</Section>

<Section><Heading>Other simplicial surfaces</Heading>
The following example constructs the real projective plane <M>P</M>,
the Klein bottle <M>K</M> and the torus <M>T</M> as simplicial complexes, using the surface genus <M>g</M> as input in the oriented case and <M>-g</M> as input in the unoriented cases. It then confirms that the connected sums <M>M=K\#P</M> and <M>N=T\#P</M> have the same integral homology.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.4aa.txt">
</Example>
</Section>

<Section><Heading>The Quillen complex</Heading>
 
<P/> Given a group <M>G </M> one can consider the partially ordered set 
<M>{\cal A}_p(G)</M>
of all non-trivial
elementary abelian <M>p</M>-subgroups of <M>G</M>, the partial order being set inclusion.
The order complex  <M>\Delta{\cal A}_p(G)</M> is a simplicial complex which is
called
 the <E>Quillen complex </E>.

<P/> The following example constructs  the
Quillen complex <M>\Delta{\cal A}_2(S_7)</M>
for the symmetric group of degree <M>7</M> and 
<M>p=2</M>. This  simplicial complex involves  <M>11291</M> simplices, of which
<M>4410</M> are <M>2</M>-simplices..

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.2.txt">
</Example>


</Section>
<Section><Heading>The Quillen complex as a reduced CW-complex</Heading>
Any simplicial complex <M>K</M> can be regarded as a regular CW complex.
Different datatypes are used in  <B>HAP</B>  for these two notions.
The following continuation of the above Quillen complex example 
constructs a regular CW complex <M>Y</M>
isomorphic to (i.e. with the same face lattice as) <M>K=\Delta{\cal A}_2(S_7)</M>. An advantage to working in the category of CW complexes is that
it may be possible to find a CW complex <M>X</M> homotopy equivalent to <M>Y</M> but with fewer cells than <M>Y</M>. The cellular chain complex <M>C_\ast(X)</M> of such a CW complex <M>X</M> is computed by the following commands. 
From the number of free generators of <M>C_\ast(X)</M>, which correspond to the cells of <M>X</M>, we see that  there is a single <M>0</M>-cell and <M>160</M> <M>2</M>-cells. Thus     
the Quillen complex
$$\Delta{\cal A}_2(S_7) \simeq \bigvee_{1\le i\le 160} S^2$$
has the homotopy type of a wedge of <M>160</M> <M>2</M>-spheres.
This homotopy equivalence 
is given in <Cite Key="ksontini" Where="(15.1)"/> where it was obtained by purely
theoretical  methods.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.3.txt">
</Example>
Note that for regular  CW complexes <M>Y</M> the function
<C>ChainComplex(Y)</C> returns the cellular chain complex <M>C_\ast(X)</M>
of a (typically non-regular) CW complex <M>X</M> homotopy equivalent to <M>Y</M>. The cellular chain complex
<M>C_\ast(Y)</M> of <M>Y</M> itself can be obtained as follows.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.4.txt">
</Example>

</Section>

<Section><Heading>Constructing a CW-structure on a knot complement</Heading>

The following commands construct the complement <M>M=S^3\setminus K</M> of the trefoil knot <M>K</M>. This complement is returned as 
 a <M>3</M>-manifold <M>M</M> with regular CW-structure involving four  <M>3</M>-cells.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.4a.txt">
</Example>

The following additional commands then show that <M>M</M> is homotopy 
equivalent to a reduced CW-complex <M>Y</M> of dimension <M>2</M> 
involving one <M>0</M>-cell, two <M>1</M>-cells and one <M>2</M>-cell. The fundamental group of <M>Y</M> is computed and used to calculate the Alexander polynomial of the trefoil
knot. 

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.4b.txt">
</Example>

</Section>

<Section><Heading>Constructing a regular CW-complex from its face lattice</Heading>

<P/>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="images/cwspace.jpg" align="center" width="250" alt="CW space"/></Alt>

<P/>The following example begins by creating a <M>2</M>-dimensional annulus <M>A</M> as 
a regular CW-complex, and testing  that it has the correct integral homology
<M>H_0(A,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z</M>, <M>H_1(A,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z</M>, <M>H_2(A,\mathbb Z)=0</M>.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.5.txt">
</Example>

<P/>Next we construct the direct product
<M>Y=A\times A\times A\times A\times A</M> of five copies of the annulus.
This is a <M>10</M>-dimensional CW complex involving <M>248832</M> cells.
It will be homotopy equivalent <M>Y\simeq X</M> to a CW complex <M>X</M>
involving fewer cells. The CW complex <M>X</M> may be non-regular.
We compute the cochain complex <M>D_\ast = {\rm Hom}_{\mathbb Z}(C_\ast(X),\mathbb Z)</M> from which the cohomology groups
<Br/><M>H^0(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z</M>,
<Br/><M>H^1(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z^5</M>,
<Br/><M>H^2(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z^{10}</M>,
<Br/><M>H^3(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z^{10}</M>,
<Br/><M>H^4(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z^5</M>,
<Br/><M>H^5(Y,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z</M>,
<Br/><M>H^6(Y,\mathbb Z)=0</M><Br/>
are obtained.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.6.txt">
</Example>

</Section>
<Section><Heading>Cup products</Heading>

<P/><B>Strategy 1: use geometric group theory in low dimensions.</B>

<P/>Continuing with the previous example, we consider 
the first and fifth generators <M>g_1^1, g_5^1\in H^1(Y,\mathbb Z) =\mathbb Z^5</M>
and establish that their cup product <M> g_1^1 \cup g_5^1 = - g_7^2 \in H^2(Y,\mathbb Z) =\mathbb Z^{10}</M> is equal to minus the seventh generator of <M>H^2(Y,\mathbb Z)</M>.
We also verify that <M>g_5^1\cup g_1^1 = - g_1^1 \cup g_5^1</M>.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.7.txt">
</Example>

<P/>This computation of low-dimensional cup products is achieved using group-theoretic methods to approximate the diagonal map <M>\Delta \colon Y \rightarrow  Y\times Y</M> in dimensions <M>\le 2</M>. In order to construct cup products in
higher degrees <B>HAP</B> invokes two further strategies.

<P/><B>Strategy 2: implement the Alexander-Whitney map for a fixed class of spaces.</B>


<P/>For simplicial complexes the cup product is implemented using the standard formula for the Alexander-Whitney chain map, together with homotopy equivalences to improve efficiency.

<P/>As a first example, the following commands construct simplicial surfaces
<M>K=(\mathbb S^1 \times \mathbb S^1) \# (\mathbb S^1 \times \mathbb S^1)</M>
and <M>L=(\mathbb S^1 \times \mathbb S^1) \vee \mathbb S^1 \vee \mathbb S^1</M>
and establish that they have the same cohomology groups. It is then shown that
the cup products <M>\cup_K\colon H^1(K,\mathbb Z)\times H^1(K,\mathbb Z) \rightarrow H^2(K,\mathbb Z)</M> and <M>\cup_L\colon H^1(L,\mathbb Z)\times H^1(L,\mathbb Z) \rightarrow H^2(L,\mathbb Z)</M> are antisymmetric bilinear forms of
 different ranks;  hence <M>K</M> and <M>L</M> have different homotopy types.
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.7c.txt">
</Example>

<P/> As a second example of the computation of cups products, the following commands construct the wedge sum
<M>W=M\vee N</M> of a <M>2</M>-dimensional orientable 
simplicial surface  of genus 2 and the <M>K3</M> complex surface which is stored as a pure simplicial complex of dimension 4. The  simplicial structure
on the <M>K3</M> surface  is taken from <Cite Key="spreerkhuenel"/>.
The commands then show that <M>H^2(W,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z^{22}</M> and
<M>H^4(W,\mathbb Z)=\mathbb Z</M>. The final commands comput the matrix <M>(x\cup y)</M> as <M>x,y</M> range over a generating set for <M>H^2(W,\mathbb Z)</M>.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.7b.txt">
</Example>

A cubical Alexander-Whitney formula can be used similarly for computing the cohomology ring of a regular CW-complex whose cells all have a cubical combinatorial face lattice. 

<P/><B>Strategy 3: Guess and verify a cellular approcimation to the diagonal map.</B>   

<P/>Many naturally occuring cell structures are neither simplicial nor cubical. For a general regular CW-complex we 
require a cellular inclusion <M>\overline Y \hookrightarrow Y\times Y</M> with projection <M>p\colon \overline Y \twoheadrightarrow Y</M> that induces isomorphisms on integral homology.
The function <C>DiagonalApproximation(Y)</C> constructs a candidate inclusion,
but the projection <M>p\colon \overline Y \twoheadrightarrow Y</M> 
needs to be tested for homology equivalence. If the candidate inclusion
 passes this test then the function <C>CupProduct(Y)</C>,  involving
 the candidate space,  can be used for cup products.  

<P/>The following example calculates <M>g_1^1 \cup g_3^2 \ne 0</M> where
<M>Y=S\times S\times A</M> is  the 
direct product of two simplicial circles <M>S</M>  and one  <M>2</M>-dimensional cubical Annulus <M>A</M> and where 
<M>g_k^n</M> denotes the <M>k</M>-th generator of <M>H^n(Y,\mathbb Z)</M>. 

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.8.txt">
</Example>
</Section>


<Section><Heading>Intersection forms of <M>4</M>-manifolds</Heading>
The cup product gives rise to the intersection form of a connected, closed,  orientable <M>4</M>-manifold <M>Y</M> is a symmetric bilinear form
<P/><M>qY\colon H^2(Y,\mathbb Z)/Torsion \times H^2(Y,\mathbb Z)/Torsion \longrightarrow \mathbb Z</M>
<P/>which we represent as a symmetric matrix.

<P/>The following example constructs the direct product <M>L=S^2\times S^2</M> of two <M>2</M>-spheres,  the connected sum 
<M>M=\mathbb CP^2 \# \overline{\mathbb CP^2}</M> of the complex projective plane <M>\mathbb CP^2</M> and its oppositely oriented version <M>\overline{\mathbb CP^2}</M>, and the connected sum
<M>M=\mathbb CP^2 \# \mathbb CP^2</M>. The manifolds <M>L</M>, <M>M</M> and <M>N</M> are each shown to have a CW-structure involving one <M>0</M>-cell, two <M>1</M>-cells and one <M>2</M>-cell. They are thus simply connected and have identical cohomology.


<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.8a.txt">
</Example>

John Milnor showed  (as a corollary to a  theorem of J. H. C. Whitehead) that the homotopy type of a simply connected 4-manifold is determined by its quadratic form. More precisely,  a form is said to be of <E>type I  (properly primitive)</E> if some diagonal entry of its matrix is odd. If every diagonal entry is even, then the form is of <E>type II (improperly primitive)</E>.
The <E>index</E> of a form is defined as the number of positive diagonal entries minus the number of negative ones, after the matrix has been diagonalized over the real numbers.

<P/><B>Theorem.</B> (Milnor <Cite Key="milnor"/>)
The oriented homotopy type of a simply connected, closed, orientable 4-manifold is determined by its second Betti number and the  index and  type of its intersetion form; except possibly in the case of a manifold with definite quadratic form of rank r > 9. 

<P/>
The following commands compute matrices representing the intersection forms <M>qL</M>, <M>qM</M>, <M>qN</M>.   


<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.8b.txt">
</Example>

Since <M>qL</M> is of type I, whereas <M>qM</M> and <M>qN</M> are  of type II 
we see that the oriented homotopy type of <M>L</M> is distinct to that of 
<M>M</M> and that of <M>N</M>. Since <M>qM</M> has index <M>2</M> and  <M>qN</M> has index <M>0</M> we see that that <M>M</M> and <M>N</M> also have distinct oriented homotopy types.

</Section>

<Section><Heading>CW maps and induced homomorphisms</Heading>

<P/>A <E>strictly cellular</E> map <M>f\colon X\rightarrow Y</M> of regular
CW-complexes is a cellular map for which the image of any cell is a cell (of 
possibly lower dimension). Inclusions of CW-subcomplexes, and projections from a direct product to a factor, are examples of such maps.
Strictly cellular maps can be represented in <B>HAP</B>, and their induced homomorphisms on (co)homology and on fundamental groups can be computed. 

<P/>
The following example begins by visualizing the trefoil knot
<M>\kappa \in \mathbb R^3</M>. It then constructs a regular 
CW structure on the complement <M>Y= D^3\setminus {\rm Nbhd}(\kappa) </M> 
of a small tubular open neighbourhood of
the knot lying inside a large closed ball <M>D^3</M>. The boundary of this
tubular neighbourhood is a <M>2</M>-dimensional CW-complex <M>B</M> homeomorphic to a torus <M>\mathbb S^1\times \mathbb S^1</M> with 
fundamental group <M>\pi_1(B)=&lt;a,b\, :\, aba^{-1}b^{-1}=1></M>.  The inclusion map
<M>f\colon B\hookrightarrow Y</M> is constructed. Then a presentation
<M>\pi_1(Y)= &lt;x,y\, |\, xy^{-1}x^{-1}yx^{-1}y^{-1}></M> 
and the induced homomorphism
$$\pi_1(B)\rightarrow \pi_1(Y), a\mapsto y^{-1}xy^2xy^{-1}, b\mapsto y $$
are computed. This induced homomorphism is an example of a <E>peripheral system</E> and is known to contain sufficient information to characterize the knot up to ambient isotopy.

<P/> Finally, it is verified that the induced homology homomorphism <M>H_2(B,\mathbb Z) \rightarrow H_2(Y,\mathbb Z)</M> is an isomomorphism.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.9.txt">
</Example>
<Alt Only="HTML">&lt;img src="images/trefoil.png" align="center" width="150" alt="trefoil knot"/></Alt>
<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/1.10.txt">
</Example>




</Section>
</Chapter>
