<Chapter><Heading>Cohomology rings and Steenrod operation for finite groups</Heading>
	<Section><Heading>Cohomology rings of finite <M>2</M>-groups</Heading>

The following example determines a presentation for the cohomology ring
<M>H^\ast(Syl_2(M_{12}),\mathbb Z_2)</M>. The Lyndon-Hochschild-Serre spectral sequence, and Groebner basis routines from <B>Singular</B>, are used to determine how much of a resolution to compute for the presentation.

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/7.0.txt">
</Example>
</Section>

<Section><Heading>Steenrod operations for finite <M>2</M>-groups</Heading>

The command <C>CohomologicalData(G,n)</C>
 prints complete information for the
	cohomology ring <M>H^\ast(G, Z_2 )</M> and steenrod operations for
	 a <M>2</M>-group <M>G</M> 
provided that the integer <M>n</M> is
at least the maximal degree of a relator in a minimal set of relators for the
ring. 

<P/>The following example produces complete information on the Steenrod algebra of group number <M>8</M> in <B>GAP</B>'s library of groups of order <M>32</M>. 
	Groebner basis routines from <B>Singular</B> are called involved in the example. (This example take over 2 hours to run. Most other groups of order 32 run significantly quicker.)


<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/7.1.txt">
</Example>

</Section>

<Section><Heading>Mod-<M>p</M> cohomology rings of finite groups</Heading>

	For a finite group <M>G</M>, prime <M>p</M> and positive integer <M>deg</M> the function <Code>ModPCohomologyRing(G,p,deg)</Code> 
		computes a finite dimensional graded ring equal to
		the cohomology ring <M>H^\ast(G,\mathbb Z_p)/\{x=0\ :\ {\rm degree}(x)>deg \}</M> .

		<P/>The following example computes the first <M>14</M> degrees of the cohomology ring <M>H^\ast(M_{11},\mathbb Z_2)</M> where <M>M_{11}</M> is the Mathieu group of order <M>7920</M>. The ring is seen to be generated by three elements <M>a_3, a_4, a_6</M> in degrees <M>3,4,5</M>.

		<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/7.1a.txt">
</Example>

</Section>
<Section><Heading>Steenrod operations on the classifying space of a finite <M>p</M>-group</Heading>

The following example constructs the first eight degrees of the
mod-<M>3</M> cohomology ring <M>H^\ast(G,\mathbb Z_3)</M>
for the group
<M>G</M> number 4 in <B>GAP</B>'s library of groups of order <M>81</M>.
It determines a minimal set of ring generators lying in degree <M>\le 8</M>
and it evaluates the Bockstein operator on these generators. 
Steenrod powers for <M>p\ge 3</M> are not implemented as  
no efficient method of implementation is known. 

<Example>
<#Include SYSTEM "tutex/7.2.txt">
</Example>

</Section>
</Chapter>
