<Chapter><Heading>Regular CW-Spaces</Heading>

<Table Align="|l|" >

<Row>
<Item>
<Index>SimplicialComplexToRegularCWSpace</Index>
<C>SimplicialComplexToRegularCWSpace(K)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a simplicial complex <M>K</M> and returns the corresponding regular CW-space. 
</Item>
</Row>


<Row>
<Item>
<Index>CubicalComplexToRegularCWSpace</Index>
<C>CubicalComplexToRegularCWSpace(K)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a pure cubical complex (or cubical complex) <M>K</M> and returns the corresponding regular CW-space.
</Item>
</Row>

<Row>
<Item>
<Index>CriticalCellsOfRegularCWSpace</Index>
<C>CriticalCellsOfRegularCWSpace(Y)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a  regular CW-space <M>Y</M> and returns the critical cells of <M>Y</M> with respect to some discrete vector field. If <M>Y</M> does not initially have a discrete vector field then one is constructed.
</Item>
</Row>

<Row>
<Item>
<Index>ChainComplex</Index>
<C>ChainComplex(Y)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a  regular CW-space <M>Y</M> and returns the cellular chain complex of a CW-space W whose cells correspond to the critical cells of <M>Y</M> with respect to some discrete vector field. If <M>Y</M> does not initially have a discrete vector field then one is constructed.
</Item>
</Row>

<Row>
<Item>
<Index>ChainComplexOfRegularCWSpace</Index>
<C>ChainComplexOfRegularCWSpace(Y)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a  regular CW-space <M>Y</M> and returns the cellular chain complex of <M>Y</M>. 
</Item>
</Row>


<Row>
<Item>
<Index>FundamentalGroup</Index>
<Index>FundamentalGroupOfRegularCWSpace</Index>
<C>FundamentalGroup(Y)</C>
<C>FundamentalGroup(Y,n)</C>

<P/>
Inputs a  regular CW-space <M>Y</M> and, optionally, the number of some 0-cell. It returns the fundamental group of <M>Y</M> based at the 0-cell <M>n</M>. The group is returned as a finitely presented group. If <M>n</M> is not specified then it is set <M>n=1</M>. The algorithm requires a discrete vector field on <M>Y</M>. If <M>Y</M> does not initially have a discrete vector field then one is constructed.

</Item>
</Row>






</Table>
</Chapter>


